Guide to the Thomas William Edmondson Papers MC 17
New York University Archives
Thomas William Edmondson Papers
1885-1917
MC 17
New York University Archives
1.25 linear feet
Thomas William Edmondson was a professor of mathematics at New York University and also served the University as Secretary of the Executive Committee of the University Council (1900-1902), Secretary of the Faculty Committee of the University Council (1903-1933), acting dean of the Graduate School (1916-1921), and Chairman of the Washington Square Collegiate Division (1913).
Edmondson, Thomas William, 1869-1938
Biography
Thomas William Edmondson was born in Skipton-in-Craven, Yorkshire, England, on June 26, 1869. His parents, Sarah Dodgson and Thomas Edmonson, Sr., were middle-class tradespeople. Thomas Edmondson, Sr. had worked himself up through the printing apprentice system and was a master printer in Skipton. He owned a small business, Edmondson & Co., Printers and Stationers, and was very active in civil affairs and the Oddfellows Society. Thomas was one of eight children. He attended elementary school in Skipton. From 1879-1888, he was the recipient of a scholarship at the Skipton Endowed Grammar School. In June 1886, he took the London University matriculation examination. When his results were published, he was first on the Honors List. He took his B.A. at London University in 1888.
In 1887, Edmondson received the Ackroyd Scholarship, which enabled him to attend Pembroke College in Cambridge. The Ackroyd was a senior mathematical scholarship. He received his B.A. from Cambridge in 1891. After getting his degree, he continued at Cambridge as an assistant tutor in mathematics and physics at the University Correspondence College and pursued graduate studies in physics, chemistry, and botany. During the summer of 1893, he immigrated to America. After a year in the United States, he was appointed to a Fellowship in Physics at Clark University in Worcester, Massachusetts. He was awarded the Ph.D. in 1896 as a result of study and research at Clark.
Following the conferral of his degree, Edmondson was appointed Assistant Professor of Physics at University College, located on the Heights campus in the Bronx. In addition to his work in the Physics Department with Professor Daniel W. Hering, he also assisted Professor Pomeroy Ladue in the Mathematics Department. In 1903, Edmondson became an assistant professor of mathematics. Following Ladue's resignation in 1906, Edmondson was appointed head of the Mathematics Department.
Professor Edmondson also served New York University as an administrator. He was Secretary of the Faculty Committee of the University Council from 1903-1933 and served as Acting Dean of the Graduate School from 1916-1921. He was also chairman of the Washington Square Collegiate Division in 1913. On August 31, 1934, Edmondson's long service to the University formally ended with his retirement. He died on November 4, 1938.
Thomas W. Edmondson was married in 1896 to Minnie Ramsden. They had no children.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Thomas William Edmondson consist primarily of correspondence with members of the Edmondson family who resided in Yorkshire, England. Some letter from friends and associates of Edmondson are also included.
The members of the Edmonson family appearing in the papers are the children and descendants of Thomas Edmondson (d. Nov. 17, 1917) and Sarah Dodgson. Their ages are unclear from the papers. The family members are listed below in alphabetical order. Dick Edmondson, married to Billie Nottingham in 1904. One child, Mary, born in 1906.
George Edmondson, married to Frances in 1914.
Harry Edmondson, married to an unnamed widow in 1916. No children. His wife died in 1918.
Jack Edmondson, married to Mabel in 1894. Five children: Katie, Sallie, Tom, Leonard, and Jessie. He also adopted Mabel’s niece, Dorothy.
Jim Edmonson, married to Bessie Dickinson in 1904. One child, Marjery, born ca. 1907.
Nan Edmondson, married to George Mattock in 1907. Two children, Mary and "Baby."
Sallie Edmondson, married to Jim Bargh in 1909. One child, Geoffrey, born in 1912. She separated from Bargh in 1916.
Thomas William Edmondson, married to Minnie Ramsden in 1896. No children.
Arrangement
Edmondson's papers are arranged chronologically by correspondent.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Edmondson family; Edmondson, Thomas William, 1869-1938; Friendly Societies Association.; Independent Order of Odd Fellows.; New York University. Dept. of Physics.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; Botany |x Study and teaching.; Clark Univeristy |z Worcester |z Mass.; Farm life |z United States |y 20th century.; Mathematics |x Study and teaching |z United States; New York University |x Administration |y 20th century.; New York University |x Faculty |x History.; New York University |x Faculty |y 19th century.; New York University |x Faculty |y 20th century.; Physics |x Study and teaching |z United States.; Skipton |z England.; World War |y 1914-1918.
- Series 1: Personal Correspondence--Family
  Edmondson family -- Correspondence; Friendly Societies Association.; Independent Order of Odd Fellows.; Botany |x Study and teaching |z United States; Clark Univeristy |z Worcester |z Mass.; Farm life |z United States | 20th century .; Mathematics |x Study and teaching |z United States; New York University |x Administration |y 20th century.; New York University |x Faculty |x History.; New York University |x Faculty |y 19th century.; New York University |x Faculty |y 20th century.; Physics |x Study and teaching |z United States.; Skipton |z England.; World War |y 1914-1918.
  - Rough Drafts of T. W. Edmondson's Correspondence, 1909-1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr. (Father of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1904 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1911 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters from Thomas Edmondson, Sr., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Clippings and Articles Relating to Thomas Edmondson, Sr. (Including his Obituary), 1906-1915 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson (Mother of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1893-1899 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters from Sarah Dodgson Edmondson, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson (Brother of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1894-1900 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1901-1906 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Jack Edmondson, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Mabel Edmondson (Wife of Jack), 1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Kate Edmondson (Daughter of Jack), 1905-1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson (Daughter of Jack), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson, 1904-1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Tom Edmondson (Son of Jack), 1911-1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Leonard Edmondson (Son of Jack), 1913-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Jessie Edmondson (Son of Jack), 1913-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Jim Edmondson (Brother of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Jim Edmondson, 1890-1899 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Jim Edmondson, 1900-1909 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Jim Edmondson, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Dick Edmondson Nottingham (Sister of T. W. Edmondson), 1909-1911 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Dick Edmondson Nottingham, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock (Sister of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, 1897-1900 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, 1901-1907 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, 1909-1914 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters from Nan Edmondson Mattock, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letters from George Mattock (Husband of Nan), 1907-1914 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters from Mary Mattock (Daughter of Nan), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson (Brother of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1893-1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1900-1904 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1905-1906 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters from Harry D. Edmondson, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letters from George Edmondson (Brother of T. W. Edmondson), 1894-1905 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Letters from George Edmondson, 1909-1914 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letters from Frances Edmondson (Wife of George), 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh (Sister of T. W. Edmondson), undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1894-1901 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1902-1909 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1910-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Sallie Edmondson Bargh, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Personal Correspondence--Friends and Associates
  - Testimonies on behalf of T. W. Edmondson from William Briggs, E. T. Hartley, Reverend C. H. Prior, and R. R. Webb, 1892-1893 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letter from Colin H. Dakers, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Card from D. W. Hering, Professor of Mathematics at NYU, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letter from H. S. Holmes, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters from F. Arnold Lees, 1890-1913 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letter from J. E. Ludlum (cousin?), 1909 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Lister Rotheray, 1889-1906 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Colin and Dorothy Stewart, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letter from G. W. Thompson [?], 1905 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters from William Whitwell, 1885-1889 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letters from William Whitwell, 1890-1901 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Letters from William Whitwell, 1902-1909 (Box 3, Folder 17)